<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!-- name="GENERATOR" content="github.com/mmarkdown/mmark Mmark Markdown Processor - mmark.miek.nl" -->
<rfc version="3" ipr="none" docName="fapi-2_0-message-signing-01" submissionType="IETF" category="std" xml:lang="en" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" consensus="true">

<front>
<title abbrev="fapi-2-message-signing">FAPI 2.0 Message Signing (Draft)</title><seriesInfo value="fapi-2_0-message-signing-01" status="standard" name="Internet-Draft"></seriesInfo>
<author initials="D." surname="Fett" fullname="Daniel Fett"><organization>yes.com</organization><address><postal><street></street>
</postal><email>mail@danielfett.de</email>
</address></author>
<author initials="D." surname="Tonge" fullname="Dave Tonge"><organization>Moneyhub Financial Technology</organization><address><postal><street></street>
</postal><email>dave@tonge.org</email>
</address></author>
<date/>
<area>Internet</area>
<workgroup>fapi</workgroup>
<keyword>security</keyword>
<keyword>openid</keyword>

<note><name>Foreword</name>
<t>The OpenID Foundation (OIDF) promotes, protects and nurtures the OpenID community and technologies. As a non-profit international standardizing body, it is comprised by over 160 participating entities (workgroup participant). The work of preparing implementer drafts and final international standards is carried out through OIDF workgroups in accordance with the OpenID Process. Participants interested in a subject for which a workgroup has been established have the right to be represented in that workgroup. International organizations, governmental and non-governmental, in liaison with OIDF, also take part in the work. OIDF collaborates closely with other standardizing bodies in the related fields.</t>
<t>Final drafts adopted by the Workgroup through consensus are circulated publicly for the public review for 60 days and for the OIDF members for voting. Publication as an OIDF Standard requires approval by at least 50% of the members casting a vote. There is a possibility that some of the elements of this document may be the subject to patent rights. OIDF shall not be held responsible for identifying any or all such patent rights.</t>
</note>

<note><name>Introduction</name>
<t>OIDF FAPI 2.0 is an API security profile based on the OAuth 2.0 Authorization
Framework <xref target="RFC6749"></xref>. This Message Signing Profile is part of the FAPI 2.0 family of specifications with a focus on providing interoperable support for non-repudiation across OAuth 2.0 based requests and responses.</t>
</note>

<note><name>Warning</name>
<t>This document is not an OIDF International Standard. It is distributed for
review and comment. It is subject to change without notice and may not be
referred to as an International Standard.</t>
<t>Recipients of this draft are invited to submit, with their comments,
notification of any relevant patent rights of which they are aware and to
provide supporting documentation.</t>
</note>

<note><name>Notational Conventions</name>
<t>The keywords &quot;shall&quot;, &quot;shall not&quot;, &quot;should&quot;, &quot;should not&quot;, &quot;may&quot;, and &quot;can&quot; in
this document are to be interpreted as described in ISO Directive Part 2
<xref target="ISODIR2"></xref>. These keywords are not used as dictionary terms such that any
occurrence of them shall be interpreted as keywords and are not to be
interpreted with their natural language meanings.</t>
</note>

</front>

<middle>

<section anchor="scope"><name>Scope</name>
<t>This document specifies the methods for Clients, Authorization Servers and Resource Servers to sign and verify messages.</t>
</section>

<section anchor="normative-references"><name>Normative references</name>
<t>See section 8 for normative references.</t>
</section>

<section anchor="terms-and-definitions"><name>Terms and definitions</name>
<t>For the purpose of this document, the terms defined in <xref target="RFC6749"></xref>, <xref target="RFC6750"></xref>, <xref target="RFC7636"></xref>, <xref target="OIDC"></xref> and ISO29100 apply.</t>
</section>

<section anchor="symbols-and-abbreviated-terms"><name>Symbols and Abbreviated terms</name>
<t><strong>API</strong> – Application Programming Interface</t>
<t><strong>HTTP</strong> – Hyper Text Transfer Protocol</t>
<t><strong>REST</strong> – Representational State Transfer</t>
<t><strong>TLS</strong> – Transport Layer Security</t>
<t><strong>URI</strong> - Uniform Resource Identifier</t>
</section>

<section anchor="message-signing-profile"><name>Message Signing Profile</name>
<t>OIDF FAPI 2.0 is an API security profile based on the OAuth 2.0 Authorization
Framework <xref target="RFC6749"></xref>. This Message Signing Profile aims to reach the security goals
laid out in the Attacker Model <xref target="attackermodel"></xref> plus the non-repudiation goals listed below.</t>
<t>All provisions of the <xref target="FAPI2_Security_Profile_ID2"></xref> apply to the Message Signing Profile
as well, with the extensions described in the following.</t>

<section anchor="profile"><name>Profile</name>
<t>In addition to the technologies used in the <xref target="FAPI2_Security_Profile_ID2"></xref>, the
following standards are used in this profile:</t>

<ul>
<li><t>OAuth 2.0 JWT Secured Authorization Request (JAR) <xref target="RFC9101"></xref> for signing authorization requests</t>
</li>
<li><t>JWT Secured Authorization Response Mode for OAuth 2.0 <xref target="JARM"></xref> for signing authorization responses</t>
</li>
<li><t>OAuth 2.0 Token Introspection <xref target="RFC7662"></xref> with <xref target="I-D.ietf-oauth-jwt-introspection-response"></xref> for signing introspection responses</t>
</li>
<li><t>HTTP Message Signatures <xref target="I-D.ietf-httpbis-message-signatures"></xref> and Digest Fields <xref target="I-D.ietf-httpbis-digest-headers"></xref>
for signing HTTP requests to and responses from Resource Servers.</t>
</li>
</ul>
<t>We understand that some ecosystems may only desire to implement 1 or 2 of the above 3, it is therefore
anticipated that a piece of software will be able to conform to each of the methods separately, i.e. there
will be separate test options for each of the following:</t>

<ul>
<li><t>Signed Authorization Requests</t>
</li>
<li><t>Signed Authorization Responses</t>
</li>
<li><t>Signed Introspection Responses</t>
</li>
<li><t>Signed HTTP Messages</t>
</li>
</ul>
</section>

<section anchor="non-repudiation"><name>Non-Repudiation</name>
<t>Beyond what is captured by the security goals and the attacker model in
<xref target="attackermodel"></xref>, parties could try to deny having sent a particular message,
for example, a payment request. For this purpose, non-repudiation is needed.</t>
<t>In the context of this specification, non-repudiation refers to the assurance that the owner of
a signature key pair that was capable of generating an existing signature corresponding to certain
data cannot convincingly deny having signed the data (<xref target="NIST.SP.800-133"></xref>).</t>
<t>This is usually achieved by providing application-level signatures that can be
stored together with the payload and meaningful metadata of a request or
response.</t>
<t>The following messages are affected by this specification:</t>

<ul>
<li><t>NR1: Pushed Authorization Requests</t>
</li>
<li><t>NR2: Authorization Requests (Front-Channel)</t>
</li>
<li><t>NR3: Authorization Responses (Front-Channel)<br />
</t>
</li>
<li><t>NR4: Introspection Responses</t>
</li>
<li><t>NR5: Resource Requests</t>
</li>
<li><t>NR6: Resource Responses</t>
</li>
</ul>
</section>

<section anchor="signing-authorization-requests"><name>Signing Authorization Requests</name>
<t>To support non-repudiation for NR1, Pushed Authorization Requests can be signed.
Because FAPI2 uses <xref target="RFC9126"></xref>, NR2 is achieved by default when the Pushed Authorization request
is signed.</t>

<section anchor="requirements-for-authorization-servers"><name>Requirements for Authorization Servers</name>
<t>Authorization servers implementing FAPI2 authorization request signing</t>

<ol>
<li><t>shall support and verify signed request objects according to JAR
<xref target="RFC9101"></xref> at the PAR endpoint <xref target="RFC9126"></xref>;</t>
</li>
<li><t>shall require the aud claim in the request object to be, or to be an array containing, the OP's Issuer Identifier URL;</t>
</li>
<li><t>shall require the request object to contain an <tt>nbf</tt> claim that is no longer than 60 minutes in the past; and</t>
</li>
<li><t>shall require the request object to contain an <tt>exp</tt> claim that has a lifetime of no longer than 60 minutes after the <tt>nbf</tt> claim.</t>
</li>
</ol>
</section>

<section anchor="requirements-for-clients"><name>Requirements for Clients</name>
<t>Clients implementing FAPI2 authorization request signing</t>

<ol>
<li><t>shall sign request objects according to JAR <xref target="RFC9101"></xref> that are sent to the PAR
endpoint <xref target="RFC9126"></xref>;</t>
</li>
<li><t>shall send the <tt>aud</tt> claim in the request object as the OP's Issuer Identifier URL;</t>
</li>
<li><t>shall send a <tt>nbf</tt> claim in the request object;</t>
</li>
<li><t>shall send an <tt>exp</tt> claim in the request object that has a lifetime of no longer than 60 minutes.</t>
</li>
</ol>
</section>
</section>

<section anchor="signing-authorization-responses"><name>Signing Authorization Responses</name>
<t>To support non-repudiation for NR3, Authorization Responses can be signed.</t>

<section anchor="requirements-for-authorization-servers-1"><name>Requirements for Authorization Servers</name>
<t>Authorization servers implementing FAPI2 authorization response signing</t>

<ol>
<li><t>shall support and issue signed authorization responses via JWT Secured Authorization
Response Mode for OAuth 2.0 <xref target="JARM"></xref>.</t>
</li>
</ol>
<t><strong>NOTE</strong>: When using <xref target="JARM"></xref> an Authorization Server should only include the iss authorization response
parameter defined by <xref target="RFC9207"></xref> inside the JWT. This is because <xref target="RFC9207"></xref> defines <tt>iss</tt>
to be an authorization response parameter, and <xref target="JARM"></xref> section 4.1 requires all authorization
response parameters to be inside the JWT.</t>
</section>

<section anchor="requirements-for-clients-1"><name>Requirements for Clients</name>
<t>Clients implementing FAPI2 authorization response signing</t>

<ol>
<li><t>shall set the <tt>response_mode</tt> to <tt>jwt</tt> in the authorization request as defined in <xref target="JARM"></xref>; and</t>
</li>
<li><t>shall verify signed authorization responses according to <xref target="JARM"></xref>.</t>
</li>
</ol>
</section>
</section>

<section anchor="signing-introspection-responses"><name>Signing Introspection Responses</name>
<t>To support non-repudiation for NR4, Introspection Responses can be signed.</t>

<section anchor="requirements-for-authorization-servers-2"><name>Requirements for Authorization Servers</name>
<t>Authorization servers implementing FAPI2 introspection response signing</t>

<ol>
<li><t>shall sign introspection responses that are issued in JWT format according to <xref target="I-D.ietf-oauth-jwt-introspection-response"></xref></t>
</li>
</ol>
</section>

<section anchor="requirements-for-clients-2"><name>Requirements for Clients</name>
<t>Clients implementing FAPI2 introspection response signing</t>

<ol>
<li><t>shall request signed token introspection responses according to <xref target="I-D.ietf-oauth-jwt-introspection-response"></xref>; and</t>
</li>
<li><t>shall verify the signed token introspection responses.</t>
</li>
</ol>
</section>
</section>

<section anchor="http-message-signing"><name>HTTP Message Signing</name>
<t>To support non-repudiation for NR5 and NR6, HTTP requests and responses
can be signed.</t>
<t>A future version of this profile expects to support HTTP Message Signing using the <em>HTTP Message Signatures</em> specification
being developed by the IETF HTTP Working Group.</t>
</section>

<section anchor="mtls-protection-of-all-endpoints"><name>MTLS Protection of all endpoints</name>
<t>Some ecosystems are choosing to require clients accessing their endpoints to supply a TLS client certificate at
endpoints that would not otherwise require a TLS client certificate (for example, the PAR endpoint when using
<tt>private_key_jwt</tt> authentication).</t>
<t>This is outside of the scope of both <xref target="RFC8705"></xref> and the FAPI standards, however in the interests of interoperability we
state that when using TLS as a transport level protection in this manner, authorization servers should expect clients to
call the endpoints located in the root of the server metadata, and not those found in <tt>mtls_endpoint_aliases</tt>.</t>
</section>
</section>

<section anchor="security-considerations"><name>Security Considerations</name>

<section anchor="authorization-response-encryption"><name>Authorization Response Encryption</name>
<t>In FAPI2, there is no confidential information in the Authorization Response, hence encryption of the Authorization Response is not required for the purposes of security or confidentiality. In addition, to achieve greater interoperability, it is not recommended to use encryption in this case.</t>
<t>Usage of PKCE in FAPI 2 provides protection for code leakage described in Section 5.4 of <xref target="JARM"></xref>.</t>
</section>
</section>

<section anchor="privacy-considerations"><name>Privacy considerations</name>
<t>In addition to the privacy considerations detailed in <xref target="FAPI2_Security_Profile_ID2"></xref> implementers should consider
the privacy implications of storing messages for the purpose of non-repudiation.</t>
<t>Such messages may well contain personally identifiable information and implementers should evaluate
whether such messages need to be stored. If they are stored then adequate access controls must be
put in place to protect that data. Such controls should follow data minimisation principles and ensure that
there are tamper-proof audit logs.</t>
</section>

<section anchor="acknowledgements"><name>Acknowledgements</name>
<t>This specification was developed by the OpenID FAPI Working Group.</t>
<t>We would like to thank Takahiko Kawasaki, Filip Skokan, Nat Sakimura, Dima Postnikov, Joseph Heenan, Brian Campbell, Ralph Bragg, Justin Richer and Lukasz Jaromin for their valuable feedback and contributions that helped to evolve this specification.</t>
</section>

</middle>

<back>
<references><name>Normative References</name>
<reference anchor="NIST.SP.800-133" target="https://nvlpubs.nist.gov/nistpubs/SpecialPublications/NIST.SP.800-133.pdf">
  <front>
    <title>NIST Special Publication 800-133</title>
    <author fullname="Elaine Barker">
      <organization></organization>
    </author>
    <author fullname="Allen Roginsky ">
      <organization></organization>
    </author>
    <date year="2019" month="July" day="23"></date>
  </front>
</reference>
<xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.6749.xml"/>
<xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.6750.xml"/>
<reference anchor="OIDC" target="http://openid.net/specs/openid-connect-core-1_0.html">
  <front>
    <title>OpenID Connect Core 1.0 incorporating errata set 1</title>
    <author fullname="Nat Sakimura" initials="N." surname="Sakimura">
      <organization>NRI</organization>
    </author>
    <author fullname="John Bradley" initials="J." surname="Bradley">
      <organization>Ping Identity</organization>
    </author>
    <author fullname="Mike Jones" initials="M." surname="Jones">
      <organization>Microsoft</organization>
    </author>
    <author fullname="Breno de Medeiros" initials="B." surname="de Medeiros">
      <organization>Google</organization>
    </author>
    <author fullname="Chuck Mortimore" initials="C." surname="Mortimore">
      <organization>Salesforce</organization>
    </author>
    <date year="2014" month="Nov" day="8"></date>
  </front>
</reference>
<xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8705.xml"/>
<reference anchor="attackermodel" target="https://openid.net/specs/fapi-2_0-attacker-model-ID2.html">
  <front>
    <title>FAPI 2.0 Attacker Model</title>
    <author fullname="Daniel Fett" initials="D." surname="Fett">
      <organization>yes.com</organization>
    </author>
    <date year="2022" month="Dec" day="7"></date>
  </front>
</reference>
<xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.9101.xml"/>
<xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.9126.xml"/>
<xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.7636.xml"/>
<reference anchor="JARM" target="https://openid.net/specs/oauth-v2-jarm-final.html">
  <front>
    <title>JWT Secured Authorization Response Mode for OAuth 2.0 (JARM)</title>
    <author fullname="Torsten Lodderstedt" initials="T." surname="Lodderstedt">
      <organization>Yes</organization>
    </author>
    <author fullname="Brian Campbell" initials="B." surname="Campbell">
      <organization>Ping</organization>
    </author>
    <date year="2022" month="Nov" day="9"></date>
  </front>
</reference>
<xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.9207.xml"/>
<reference anchor="ISODIR2" target="https://www.iso.org/sites/directives/current/part2/index.xhtml">
  <front>
    <title>ISO/IEC Directives Part 2 - </title>
    <author fullname="International Organization for Standardization">
      <organization></organization>
    </author>
    <date></date>
  </front>
</reference>
<reference anchor="FAPI2_Security_Profile_ID2" target="https://openid.net/specs/fapi-2_0-security-profile-ID2.html">
  <front>
    <title>FAPI 2.0 Security Profile</title>
    <author fullname="Daniel Fett" initials="D." surname="Fett">
      <organization>yes.com</organization>
    </author>
    <date year="2022" month="Dec" day="7"></date>
  </front>
</reference>
<xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.7662.xml"/>
<xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml-ids/reference.I-D.ietf-oauth-jwt-introspection-response.xml"/>
</references>
<references><name>Informative References</name>
<xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml-ids/reference.I-D.ietf-httpbis-message-signatures.xml"/>
<xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml-ids/reference.I-D.ietf-httpbis-digest-headers.xml"/>
</references>

<section anchor="notices"><name>Notices</name>
<t>Copyright (c) 2023 The OpenID Foundation.</t>
<t>The OpenID Foundation (OIDF) grants to any Contributor, developer, implementer, or other interested party a non-exclusive, royalty free, worldwide copyright license to reproduce, prepare derivative works from, distribute, perform and display, this Implementers Draft or Final Specification solely for the purposes of (i) developing specifications, and (ii) implementing Implementers Drafts and Final Specifications based on such documents, provided that attribution be made to the OIDF as the source of the material, but that such attribution does not indicate an endorsement by the OIDF.</t>
<t>The technology described in this specification was made available from contributions from various sources, including members of the OpenID Foundation and others. Although the OpenID Foundation has taken steps to help ensure that the technology is available for distribution, it takes no position regarding the validity or scope of any intellectual property or other rights that might be claimed to pertain to the implementation or use of the technology described in this specification or the extent to which any license under such rights might or might not be available; neither does it represent that it has made any independent effort to identify any such rights. The OpenID Foundation and the contributors to this specification make no (and hereby expressly disclaim any) warranties (express, implied, or otherwise), including implied warranties of merchantability, non-infringement, fitness for a particular purpose, or title, related to this specification, and the entire risk as to implementing this specification is assumed by the implementer. The OpenID Intellectual Property Rights policy requires contributors to offer a patent promise not to assert certain patent claims against other contributors and against implementers. The OpenID Foundation invites any interested party to bring to its attention any copyrights, patents, patent applications, or other proprietary rights that may cover technology that may be required to practice this specification.</t>
</section>

</back>

</rfc>
