<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='http://xml.resource.org/authoring/rfc2629.xslt' ?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM 'rfc2629.dtd' [
  <!ENTITY OpenID.Core PUBLIC '' 'https://openid.net/bibxml/reference.OpenID.Core.xml'>
  <!ENTITY OpenID.Registration PUBLIC '' 'https://openid.net/bibxml/reference.OpenID.Registration.xml'>
]>
<!--
  NOTE:  This XML file is input used to produce the authoritative copy of an
  OpenID Foundation specification.  The authoritative copy is the HTML output.
  This XML source file is not authoritative.  The statement ipr="none" is
  present only to satisfy the document compilation tool and is not indicative
  of the IPR status of this specification.  The IPR for this specification is
  described in the "Notices" section.  This is a public OpenID Foundation
  document and not a private document, as the private="..." declaration could
  be taken to indicate.
-->
<rfc category="std" docName="openid-connect-modrna-client-initiated-backchannel-authentication-profile-03" ipr="none">

  <?rfc toc="yes" ?>
  <?rfc tocdepth="5" ?>
  <?rfc symrefs="yes" ?>
  <?rfc sortrefs="yes"?>
  <?rfc strict="yes" ?>
  <?rfc iprnotified="no" ?>
  <?rfc private="Draft" ?>
  
  <front>
    <title abbrev="MODRNA CIBA Profile">
            MODRNA: Client Initiated Backchannel Authentication Profile 1.0 draft-03</title>


    <author fullname="Gonzalo Fernandez Rodriguez" initials="G." surname="Fernandez">
      <organization abbrev="Telefonica">Telefonica I+D</organization>
      <address>
        <email>gonzalo.fernandezrodriguez@telefonica.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Florian Walter" initials="F." surname="Walter">
      <organization abbrev="">Deutsche Telekom AG</organization>
      <address>
        <email>F.Walter@telekom.de</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Axel Nennker" initials="A." surname="Nennker">
      <organization abbrev="">Deutsche Telekom AG</organization>
      <address>
        <email>axel.nennker@telekom.de</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Dave Tonge" initials="D." surname="Tonge">
      <organization abbrev="Moneyhub">Moneyhub</organization>
      <address>
        <email>dave.tonge@moneyhub.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Bjorn Hjelm" initials="B." surname="Hjelm">
      <organization abbrev="Verizon">Verizon</organization>
      <address>
        <email>bjorn.hjelm@verizon.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <date day="30" month="April" year="2020"/>
    
    <workgroup>OpenID MODRNA Working Group</workgroup>

    <abstract>    
      <t>
        <xref target="CIBA.Core">OpenID Connect Client Initiated Backchannel Authentication Flow</xref> [CIBA Core] 
        is an authentication flow like OpenID Connect but with a direct Relying Party to OpenID Provider communication 
        without redirects through the user's browser. The MODRNA Client Initiated Backchannel Authentication (CIBA)
        Profile is a profile of <xref target="CIBA.Core">OpenID Connect Client Initiated Backchannel Authentication Flow</xref> 
        [CIBA Core] to be used when requesting authentication from Mobile Network Operators (MNOs).
      </t>
    </abstract>
  </front>

  <middle>
    <section anchor="Introduction" title="Introduction">
      <t>
        <xref target="CIBA.Core">OpenID Connect Client Initiated Backchannel Authentication Flow</xref> [CIBA Core] 
        is an authentication flow like OpenID Connect in which a Relying Party, that can obtain a valid identifier for 
        the user they want to authenticate, will be able to initiate an interaction flow to authenticate their users without 
        having end-user interaction from the consumption device. The flow involves direct communication from the Client to 
        the OpenID Provider without redirect through the user's browser (consumption device).
      </t>
      <t>
        This specification is a MODRNA profile of the <xref target="CIBA.Core">OpenID Connect Client Initiated Backchannel 
        Authentication Flow</xref> [CIBA.Core] to be used when requesting authentication from Mobile Network Operators (MNOs) 
        and includes guidance specific to that context.
      </t>
 
      <section anchor="rnc" title="Requirements Notation and Conventions">
        <t>
          The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL NOT",
          "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in this
          document are to be interpreted as described in <xref target="RFC2119"/>.
        </t>

        <t>
          Throughout this document, values are quoted to indicate that they are
          to be taken literally. When using these values in protocol messages, the
          quotes MUST NOT be used as part of the value.
        </t>
      </section>
    </section>

   <section anchor="terminology" title="Terminology">
      <t>
        This specification uses the terms "OpenID Provider (OP)" and "Relying Party (RP)" as
        defined by <xref target="OpenID.Core">OpenID Connect Core</xref> [OpenID.Core]. Furthermore, it uses the term "Client" as
        defined by <xref target="RFC6749">OAuth 2.0</xref>. OAuth 2.0 Authorization Servers implementing OpenID Connect
        and CIBA are also referred to as OpenID Providers (OPs). 
        OAuth 2.0 Clients using OpenID Connect and CIBA are also referred to as Relying Parties (RPs).
        This specification also uses the following terms: 
      </t>
      <t>
        <list style="hanging">
          <t hangText="Mobile Network Operator (MNO)">
          A provider of wireless communication services that owns or controls the wireless network elements necessary to sell and 
          deliver services to an end user.
          </t>
          <t hangText="Mobile Station International Subscriber Directory Number (MSISDN)">
          A telephone number uniquely identifying a subscription in a mobile network.
          </t>          
          <t hangText="Consumption Device (CD)">
            The Consumption Device is the device that helps the user consume the service.
            In the CIBA use case, the user is not necessarily in control of the CD. For example, the CD may be in the control
            of an RP agent (e.g. at a bank teller) or may be an RP controlled device (e.g. a petrol pump).
          </t>
          <t hangText="Authentication Device (AD)">
            The device on which the user will authenticate and authorize the request, often a smartphone. 
          </t>
        </list>
      </t>
    </section>

   <section anchor="overview" title="Overview">
      <t>Client Initiated Backchannel Authentication (CIBA) enables a Client to initiate the authentication of an end-user 
        by means of out-of-band mechanisms. The <xref target="CIBA.Core">OpenID Connect Client Initiated Backchannel 
        Authentication Flow</xref> [CIBA Core] defines three ways to deliver the tokens and step 3 will cover the requirements 
        for this profile.
      </t>
      <t>
      <list style="numbers">
		    <t>
          The Client shall make an "HTTP POST" request to the Backchannel Authentication Endpoint to ask for end-user
          authentication. 
		    </t>
		    <t>
          The OP will respond immediately with a unique identifier that identifies that authentication while it tries 
          to authenticate the user in the background. 
		    </t>
		    <t>
          The Client will receive the ID Token, Access Token and optionally Refresh Token by means of either the Poll or 
          Push modes. This choice MUST be established by the Client at registration time.
          <list style="hanging">
           <t hangText="Poll Mode">
              When configured in Poll mode, the Client will poll the token endpoint to get a response with the tokens. 
            </t>
            <t hangText="Push Mode">
              When configured in Push mode, the OP will send a request with the tokens to a callback URI previously
              registered by the Client.
            </t>

          </list>
        </t>
		  </list>
      </t>
      <section anchor="use_cases" title="Examples of Use Cases">
        <t>The following use cases are non-normative examples to illustrate the usage of this specification.</t>
        <t>
          <list style="numbers">
            <t>A call center agent wants to authenticate a caller. 
            Using additional scopes like e.g. "profile" or "phone" the call center agent would get access to claims
            about the user like "phone_number" and "phone_number_verified".
            </t>
            <t>
              An IDP wants to offer the ability for its relying parties to request "step-up" authorisation via a decoupled device
            </t>
    
          </list>
        </t>
      </section>
    </section>
    <section anchor="auth_request" title="Authentication Request">
      <t>
        The Authentication Request has the following differences from the 
        <xref target="CIBA.Core">OpenID Connect Client Initiated Backchannel Authentication Flow</xref> [CIBA Core]:
      </t>
       <t>
          <list style="hanging">
            <t hangText="acr_values">
              REQUIRED. This value is required as defined in <xref
              target="MODRNA.Authentication">OpenID Connect MODRNA Authentication Profile</xref> [MODRNA.Authentication].
            </t>         
          </list>
        </t>
        <t>
          Note: While the structure of a <spanx style="verb">login_hint</spanx> is undefined, in a 
          mobile context a login_hint is likely to contain a MSISDN. 
        </t>
        <t>
          Note: An ecosystem can protect the pricacy of a user's MSISDN and other personally identifiable
          information through the use of a discovery service. The discovery service can return an 
          encrypted <spanx style="verb">login_hint_token</spanx> for use in a CIBA flow.
        </t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="security_considerations" title="Security Considerations">
      <t>
       While this profile suports CIBA push mode, implementers should only implement that mode if 
       the constraints of an environment require it, e.g. high latency environments. Poll mode 
       is preferred as this method of token delivery is the same as other OAuth 2.0  
       based flows, and therefore more likely to have had appropriate security review. 
      </t>

    </section>

    <section anchor="privacy_considerations" title="Privacy Considerations">
      <t>
        Using MODRNA CIBA Profile it is possible for the Client
        to authenticate a user without knowing e.g. the MSISDN of the user.
        Users might be reluctant to provide their MSISDN to Clients because they fear
        misuse through automated calls or their number being leaked.
        The login hint token can be encrypted in order to protect the user's MSISDN from 
        being revealed to the Client unintentionally.
      </t>

      <t>
        The section <xref target="SimAppletExample" format="title"/> shows an example to illustrate
        the usage of MODRNA CIBA Profile specification to authenticate a user with a SIM Applet Authenticator.
      </t>
    </section>

  </middle>

  <back>
    <references title="Normative References">
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.2119"?>
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.6750"?>
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.7519"?> <!-- JWT -->

      &OpenID.Core;
      &OpenID.Registration;

      <reference anchor="CIBA.Core"
                 target="https://openid.net/specs/openid-client-initiated-backchannel-authentication-core-1_0.html">
        <front>
          <title>OpenID Client Initiated Backchannel Authentication Flow - Core 1.0</title>
          <author fullname="Gonzalo Fernandez Rodriguez" initials="G." surname="Fernandez">
            <organization abbrev="Telefonica">Telefonica I+D</organization>
          </author>
          <author fullname="Florian Walter" initials="F." surname="Walter">
            <organization abbrev="">Deutsche Telekom AG</organization>
          </author>
          <author fullname="Axel Nennker" initials="A." surname="Nennker">
            <organization abbrev="">Deutsche Telekom AG</organization>
          </author>
          <author fullname="Dave Tonge" initials="D." surname="Tonge">
            <organization abbrev="Moneyhub">Moneyhub</organization>
          </author>
          <author fullname="Brian Campbell" initials="B." surname="Campbell">
            <organization abbrev="Ping Identity">Ping Identity</organization>
          </author>
          <date day="22" month="January" year="2020"/>
        </front>
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="MODRNA.Authentication"
                 target="https://openid.net/specs/openid-connect-modrna-authentication-1_0.html">
        <front>
          <title>OpenID Connect Mobile Authentication Profile 1.0</title>
          <author fullname="Joerg Connotte" initials="J." surname="Connotte">
            <organization abbrev="">Deutsche Telekom</organization>
          </author>
          <author fullname="John Bradley" initials="J." surname="Bradley">
            <organization abbrev="Ping Identity">Ping Identity</organization>
          </author>
          <date day="6" month="March" year="2017"/>
        </front>
      </reference>

      <?rfc include="reference.I-D.draft-ietf-oauth-mtls-12"?>

    </references>
    
    <references title="Informative References">

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.6749"?>
      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.8414'?> <!-- OAuth AS metadata -->
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.7591"?> <!-- Client Registration -->

      <?rfc include="reference.I-D.draft-ietf-oauth-device-flow-13"?>

      

      <reference anchor="ETSI102204" target="https://www.etsi.org/deliver/etsi_ts/102200_102299/102204/01.01.04_60/ts_102204v010104p.pdf">
        <front>
          <title>Mobile Commerce (M-COMM) Mobile Signature Service; Web Service Interface</title>
          <author fullname="ETSI TS 102 204 V1.1.4 (2003-08)" initials="ETSI">
            <organization abbrev="ETSI">European Telecommunications Standards Institute</organization>
          </author>
          <date year="2003"/>
        </front>
      </reference>


    </references>

    <section anchor="SimAppletExample" title="Example Flow">
      <t>
        This is a non-normative example where a challenge authentication is launched by the OP to an applet that is running in the
        end-user device's SIM. Such applet implements an authenticator that validates a Pin Code entered by the end-user.
      </t>
      <t>
        This authenticator would be implemented through the so-called MSSP (Mobile Signature Subscriber Provider) Server.
        When the Backchannel Authentication Endpoint receives the request to authenticate the user and once it knows the user's MSISDN, it makes a call
        to the MSSP Server which builds a binary Class 2 SMS that is sent to the SIM card of the user where the applet is located.
      </t>

      <t>
        This Class 2 SMS is not really sent directly from the MSSP but through the OTA (Over the air) platform which in turn signs 
        and encrypts the message using a pair of keys (kyc, kyd) unique per each SIM Card.
      </t>
        
      <t>
        Once the message reaches the SIM Card, it is decrypted by the CardManager and the signature is verified (thanks to the same pair of keys: kyc, kyd).
        If everything is ok, the CardManager gives the message to the applet that checks the signature (the another one made by the MSSP) and displays the challenge
        through a popup using the mobile phone native interface) and the user is prompted to enter a Pin Code that is validated locally.
        If the Pin Code is correct, the applet builds an OK response and signs it with the same key used by the MSSP to sign the request, this 
        response is sent as a Class 3 message to the MSSP that checks the signature, and builds the id_token and the access_token to be returned to the Client.
      </t>
      <figure>
        <artwork>
          <![CDATA[

+-----+                    +-----+                      +-------+                 +-----------+          +-------+
| RP  |                    | OP  |                      | MSSP  |                 | SIMApplet |          | User  |
+-----+                    +-----+                      +-------+                 +-----------+          +-------+
   |                          |                             |                           |                    |
   | 1. POST /bc-authorize    |                             |                           |                    |
   |------------------------->|                             |                           |                    |
   |                          |                             |                           |                    |
   |           2. HTTP 200 OK |                             |                           |                    |
   |<-------------------------|                             |                           |                    |
   |                          |                             |                           |                    |
   |                          | 3. Authenticate(MSISDN)     |                           |                    |
   |                          |---------------------------->|                           |                    |
   |                          |                             |                           |                    |
   |                          |                             | 4. Challenge              |                    |
   |                          |                             |-------------------------->|                    |
   |                          |                             |                           |                    |
   |                          |                             |                           | 7. Verify Req      |
   |                          |                             |                           |--------------      |
   |                          |                             |                           |             |      |
   |                          |                             |                           |<-------------      |
   |                          |                             |                           |                    |
   |                          |                             |                           | 8. Challenge       |
   |                          |                             |                           |------------------->|
   |                          |                             |                           |                    |
   |                          |                             |                           |        9. Pin Code |
   |                          |                             |                           |<-------------------|
   |                          |                             |                           |                    |
   |                          |                             |                           | 10. Verify Pin     |
   |                          |                             |                           |---------------     |
   |                          |                             |                           |              |     |
   |                          |                             |                           |<--------------     |
   |                          |                             |                           |                    |
   |                          |                             |           11. Response OK |                    |
   |                          |                             |<--------------------------|                    |
   |                          |                             |                           |                    |
   |                          |                             | 13. Verify Response       |                    |
   |                          |                             |--------------------       |                    |
   |                          |                             |                   |       |                    |
   |                          |                             |<-------------------       |                    |
   |                          |                             |                           |                    |
   |                          |       14. Authentication OK |                           |                    |
   |                          |<----------------------------|                           |                    |
   |                          |                             |                           |                    |
   |                          | 15. Generate Tokens         |                           |                    |
   |                          |--------------------         |                           |                    |
   |                          |                   |         |                           |                    |
   |                          |<-------------------         |                           |                    |
   |                          |                             |                           |                    |
   |             16. POST /cb |                             |                           |                    |
   |<-------------------------|                             |                           |                    |
   |                          |                             |                           |                    |


          ]]>
        </artwork>
      </figure>
      <t>
        Many of the details have advisedly been excluded in order to simplify the flow described. To go into details of how to 
        implement a Mobile Signature Service look at <xref target="ETSI102204" format="title"/>.
      </t>

    </section>

    <section anchor="Acknowledgements" title="Acknowledgements">
      <t>The following have contributed to the development of this specification.</t>
    </section>


    <section anchor="Notices" title="Notices">
      <t>Copyright (c) 2020 The OpenID Foundation.</t>
      <t>
        The OpenID Foundation (OIDF) grants to any Contributor, developer, 
        implementer, or other interested party a non-exclusive, royalty free, 
        worldwide copyright license to reproduce, prepare derivative works from, 
        distribute, perform and display, this Implementers Draft or 
        Final Specification solely for the purposes of (i) developing 
        specifications, and (ii) implementing Implementers Drafts and 
        Final Specifications based on such documents, provided that attribution 
        be made to the OIDF as the source of the material, but that such attribution 
        does not indicate an endorsement by the OIDF.
      </t>
      <t>
        The technology described in this specification was 
        made available from contributions from various sources, 
        including members of the OpenID Foundation and others.  
        Although the OpenID Foundation has taken steps to help ensure 
        that the technology is available for distribution, it takes 
        no position regarding the validity or scope of any intellectual 
        property or other rights that might be claimed to pertain to 
        the implementation or use of the technology described in 
        this specification or the extent to which any license under 
        such rights might or might not be available; neither does it 
        represent that it has made any independent effort to identify 
        any such rights.  The OpenID Foundation and the contributors 
        to this specification make no (and hereby expressly disclaim any) 
        warranties (express, implied, or otherwise), including implied 
        warranties of merchantability, non-infringement, fitness for 
        a particular purpose, or title, related to this specification, 
        and the entire risk as to implementing this specification is 
        assumed by the implementer.  The OpenID Intellectual 
        Property Rights policy requires contributors to offer 
        a patent promise not to assert certain patent claims against 
        other contributors and against implementers.  The OpenID Foundation invites 
        any interested party to bring to its attention any copyrights, 
        patents, patent applications, or other proprietary rights 
        that may cover technology that may be required to practice 
        this specification.
      </t>
    </section>

    <section anchor='History' title='Document History'>
      <t>[[ To be removed from the final specification ]]</t>
      <t>-01 
        <list style='symbols'>
          <t>Initial draft of mobile profile</t>
        </list>
      </t>
      <t>-02 
        <list style='symbols'>
          <t>Tidied up draft, removing todos</t>
        </list>
      </t>
      <t>-03 
        <list style='symbols'>
          <t>Updated title, version numbering and authors.</t>
          <t>Updated text in the abstract and introduction sections.</t>
          <t>Added terminology section.</t>
          <t>Updated reference section with CIBA Core and MODRNA spec. and added the references throughout the spec.</t>
          <t>Added Overview section and included examples of use cases.</t>
          <t>Removed ping mode based on initial version of CIBA.</t>
        </list>
      </t>
    </section>
  </back>
</rfc>