<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='http://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/authoring/rfc2629.xslt' ?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc PUBLIC "-//IETF//DTD RFC 2629//EN"
"http://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/authoring/rfc2629.dtd">
<!--
  NOTE:  This XML file is input used to produce the authoritative copy of an
  OpenID Foundation specification.  The authoritative copy is the HTML output.
  This XML source file is not authoritative.  The statement ipr="none" is
  present only to satisfy the document compilation tool and is not indicative
  of the IPR status of this specification.  The IPR for this specification is
  described in the "Notices" section.  This is a public OpenID Foundation
  document and not a private document, as the private="..." declaration could
  be taken to indicate.
-->
<rfc category="std" docName="openid-heart-fhir-uma" ipr="none">
  <?rfc toc="yes" ?>

  <?rfc tocdepth="5" ?>

  <?rfc symrefs="yes" ?>

  <?rfc sortrefs="yes"?>

  <?rfc strict="yes" ?>

  <?rfc iprnotified="no" ?>

  <?rfc private="Final" ?>

  <front>
    <title abbrev="HEART FHIR UMA">Health Relationship Trust Profile for Fast
    Healthcare Interoperability Resources (FHIR) UMA Resources</title>

    <author fullname="Justin Richer" initials="J." role="editor"
            surname="Richer">
      <address>
        <email>openid@justin.richer.org</email>

        <uri/>
      </address>
    </author>

    <date day="25" month="May" year="2017"/>

    <workgroup>OpenID Heart Working Group</workgroup>

    <abstract>
      <t>FHIR is an HTTP-based, resource-oriented RESTful API based on a set
      of clinical, administrative, financial, and infrastructure resource
      definitions. The API supports create, read, update, delete, and search
      operations, as well as a framework for ad-hoc operations.</t>

      <t>The User-Managed Access (UMA) protocol framework defines a mechanism
      to allow a resource owner to delegate access to a protected resource for
      a client application used by a requesting party (identified by a set of
      claims), optionally limited by a set of scopes.</t>

      <t>This specification profiles the resource types and claim types to be
      used with the FHIR protocol to increase baseline security, provide
      greater interoperability, and structure deployments in a manner
      specifically applicable to (but not limited to) the healthcare
      domain.</t>
    </abstract>
  </front>

  <middle>
    <section anchor="Introduction" title="Introduction">
      <t>This document profiles the UMA authorization framework for use in the
      context of securing Representational State Transfer (RESTful) interfaces
      using the Fast Health Interoperable Resources (FHIR) protocol. The FHIR
      OAuth 2.0 profile defined in this document serve to define a baseline
      set of FHIR OAuth scopes suitable for a wide range of use cases, while
      maintaining reasonable ease of implementation and functionality.</t>

      <section anchor="rnc" title="Requirements Notation and Conventions">
        <t>The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL NOT",
        "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "NOT RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and
        "OPTIONAL" in this document are to be interpreted as described in
        <xref target="RFC2119">RFC 2119</xref>.</t>

        <t>All uses of <xref target="RFC7517">JSON Web Signature (JWS)</xref>
        and <xref target="RFC7518">JSON Web Encryption (JWE)</xref> data
        structures in this specification utilize the JWS Compact Serialization
        or the JWE Compact Serialization; the JWS JSON Serialization and the
        JWE JSON Serialization are not used.</t>
      </section>

      <section anchor="Terminology" title="Terminology">
        <t>This specification uses the terms "Access Token", "Authorization
        Code", "Authorization Endpoint", "Authorization Grant", "Authorization
        Server", "Client", "Client Authentication", "Client Identifier",
        "Client Secret", "Grant Type", "Protected Resource", "Redirection
        URI", "Refresh Token", "Resource Owner", "Resource Server", "Response
        Type", and "Token Endpoint" defined by <xref target="RFC6749">OAuth
        2.0</xref>, the terms "Claim Name", "Claim Value", and "JSON Web Token
        (JWT)" defined by <xref target="RFC7519">JSON Web Token (JWT)</xref>,
        and the terms defined by <xref target="OpenID.Core">OpenID Connect
        Core 1.0</xref>.</t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section anchor="resource-reg" title="Resource Registration">
      <t>Resource sets MUST be registered by the resource server at the
      authorization server before they can be accessed by clients.</t>

      <t>Resources MUST be structured in such a way that an unauthorized
      request to the resource (with no access token) can be mapped to an
      appropriate resource set, resource owner, and authorization server.</t>

      <section title="Resource Types">
        <t>Resource sets MUST include a <spanx style="verb">type</spanx>
        identifier describing the kind of FHIR resources being protected,
        based on the FHIR compartment or resource that fits the data being
        protected.</t>

        <t>For compartments, this value SHALL be a URL of the form <spanx
        style="verb">http://www.hl7.org/fhir/compartmentdefinition-&lt;compartmentname&gt;.html</spanx>,
        where <spanx style="verb">&lt;compartmentname&gt;</spanx> is the FHIR
        compartment type designation as found on <spanx style="verb">http://www.hl7.org/fhir/compartmentdefinition.html</spanx>.</t>

        <t>For resources, this value SHALL be a URL in the form <spanx
        style="verb">http://www.hl7.org/fhir/&lt;resourcename&gt;.html</spanx>,
        where <spanx style="verb">&lt;resourcename&gt;</spanx> is the FHIR
        resource type designation as found on <spanx style="verb">http://www.hl7.org/fhir/resourcelist.html</spanx>.</t>
      </section>

      <section anchor="Access" title="Scopes">
        <t>Resource sets MUST specify at least one resource access scope as
        defined in section 2 of <xref target="HEART.OAuth2.FHIR"/>.</t>

        <t>Additionally, the resource MAY use any of the scopes defined in
        <xref target="HEART.OAuth2.FHIR"/> section 3 regarding confidentiality
        and sensitivity, or in section 4 regarding emergency (break the
        glass).</t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section title="Claims Presentation">
      <t>For determining access to healthcare records, it's useful to define a
      standard set of claims that can be used across domains to represent
      common access conditions. The following claims are defined as additional
      claims to be included in a user's OpenID Connect ID token or UserInfo
      Endpoint response.</t>

      <t>The claims used for processing MUST be considered in the context of
      the issuer of these claims. The method by which an authorization server
      determines which issuers are allowed to make which claims is out of
      scope of this specification.</t>

      <section title="Membership in an organization">
        <t>To include all members of an organization, such as a hospital,
        include the <spanx style="verb">org</spanx> claim.</t>

        <t><list style="hanging">
            <t hangText="org">Array of machine-readable URIs representing
            organizations that the user is a part of.</t>
          </list></t>

        <t>If the value of <spanx style="verb">org</spanx> is the same as the
        <spanx style="verb">iss</spanx> of the ID token, it SHOULD be taken as
        authoritative.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="Professional credentialing status">
        <t>To reference licenses, accreditations, or other professional
        credentials held by the current user, include the <spanx style="verb">pro</spanx>
        claim. These are generally for things such as specific medical
        licenses or degrees.</t>

        <t><list style="hanging">
            <t hangText="pro">Array of machine-readable values representing
            the professional credential held by the current user.</t>
          </list></t>

        <t>Each <spanx style="verb">pro</spanx> value consists of a JSON
        object with the following members:</t>

        <t><list style="hanging">
            <t hangText="src">URI representing the authority conveying the
            professional credential on the user, such as a state or regulatory
            group</t>

            <t hangText="val">String value representing the nature of the
            processional credential held.</t>
          </list></t>

        <t>The value of the professional credential is dependent on and
        potentially defined in the context of the authoritative source. An
        example list of professional values can be found at <spanx
        style="verb">http://www.hl7.org/fhir/v2/0360/2.7/index.html</spanx>.</t>

        <t>The means by which a given organization is trusted to convey a
        given professional status to an organization is outside the scope of
        this document. Note that the <spanx style="verb">src</spanx> claim
        here is likely to be different from the <spanx style="verb">iss</spanx>
        of the ID token, and the means by which an issuer is trusted to assert
        holding of accreditation from a particular source is outside the scope
        of this specification.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="Specific identification of parties">
        <t>To reference an individual, an authorization server MAY use the
        email claim.</t>

        <t>To determine which server is authoritative for a given email domain
        at runtime, an authorization server MAY take the target email address
        and perform a <xref target="RFC7033">webfinger</xref> lookup of the
        OpenID Connect issuer. The discovered issuer SHOULD be considered
        canonical for email addresses from that domain.</t>
      </section>

      <section anchor="emergency-access" title="Emergency access">
        <t>Those with a need for emergency access can be flagged with the
        <spanx style="verb">er</spanx> claim.</t>

        <t><list style="hanging">
            <t hangText="er">Boolean indicating, if present and true, that the
            current user has emergency responder status and SHOULD be given
            access to records for emergency use without requiring the input of
            the resource owner by the way of a "break the glass" emergency
            access policy (see <xref target="break-the-glass"/>)</t>
          </list></t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section title="Policy Development">
      <t>While a wide range of policies and policy engines are available to
      implementors, there are some general recommendations regarding the use
      of such policies with medical records.</t>

      <t>An authorization server SHOULD provision a newly registered resource
      set with a default-deny policy, such that sharing is allowed only when
      the resource owner explicitly shares it.</t>

      <t>Authorization servers MUST provide resource owners with the means to
      set policies based on any of the claims in this document referencing any
      of the scopes allowed in <xref target="Access"/>.</t>

      <t>Authorization servers MUST provide a means for resource owners to
      audit which policies are in effect at any protected resources controlled
      by the resource owner.</t>

      <section anchor="break-the-glass"
               title="&quot;Break the glass&quot; emergency access policies">
        <t>Authorization servers SHOULD provide a mechanism to specify a
        policy to accept certain flags, including but not limited to the
        <spanx style="verb">er</spanx> claim provided by trusted identity
        providers, to gain access to the resource set without direct
        involvement by the resource owner. This type of policy MUST include
        access to the <spanx style="verb">btg</spanx> scope specified in the
        <xref target="HEART.OAuth2.FHIR">HEART OAuth FHIR profile</xref>.</t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section title="Security considerations">
      <t>All claims presented to an authorization server need to be taken in
      the context of the presenter and issuer of the claim, and therefore
      trusted only in so much as the issuer is trusted to assert such claims.
      For example, an end user run identity provider should not be considered
      the canonical source for medical license information, unless the
      authorization server accepting the assertions has an external
      relationship with that identity provider that provides such trust.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Privacy considerations">
      <t>Since the initial request for a resource is made in an unauthorized
      and unauthenticated context, such requests are by definition open to all
      users. The response of that request includes a pointer to the
      authorization server to query for an access token and present claims. If
      it is known out of band that authorization server is owned and
      controlled by a single user, or visiting the authorization server
      contains other identifying information, then an unauthenticated and
      unauthorized client would be able to tell which resource owner is
      associated with a given resource. In the FHIR API, this means that a
      client would be able to discern which patient a given record is for
      without being authorized for that information and without the resource
      server giving that information explicitly. Other information about the
      resource owner, such as organizational affiliation or group membership,
      may be gained from this transaction as well.</t>
    </section>
  </middle>

  <back>
    <references title="Normative References">
      <?rfc include="http://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2119"?>

      <?rfc include="http://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2246"?>

      <?rfc include='http://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3986'?>

      <?rfc include="http://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5246"?>

      <?rfc include="http://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5322"?>

      <?rfc include="http://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5646"?>

      <?rfc include="http://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5785"?>

      <?rfc include="http://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.6125"?>

      <?rfc include="http://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.6749"?>

      <?rfc include="http://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.6750"?>

      <?rfc include="http://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.6819"?>

      <?rfc include="http://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.7033"?>

      <?rfc include="http://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.7517"?>

      <?rfc include="http://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.7518"?>

      <?rfc include="http://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.7519"?>

      <reference anchor="OpenID.Core">
        <front>
          <title>OpenID Connect Core 1.0</title>

          <author fullname="Nat Sakimura" initials="N." surname="Sakimura">
            <organization abbrev="NRI">Nomura Research Institute,
            Ltd.</organization>
          </author>

          <author fullname="John Bradley" initials="J." surname="Bradley">
            <organization abbrev="Ping Identity">Ping Identity</organization>
          </author>

          <author fullname="Michael B. Jones" initials="M.B." surname="Jones">
            <organization abbrev="Microsoft">Microsoft</organization>
          </author>

          <author fullname="Breno de Medeiros" initials="B."
                  surname="de Medeiros">
            <organization abbrev="Google">Google</organization>
          </author>

          <author fullname="Chuck Mortimore" initials="C." surname="Mortimore">
            <organization abbrev="Salesforce">Salesforce</organization>
          </author>

          <date day="8" month="November" year="2014"/>
        </front>

        <format target="http://openid.net/specs/openid-connect-core-1_0.html"
                type="HTML"/>
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="HEART.OAuth2"
                 target="http://openid.net/specs/openid-heart-oauth2-1_0.html">
        <front>
          <title>Health Relationship Trust Profile for OAuth 2.0</title>

          <author fullname="Justin Richer" initials="J." role="editor"
                  surname="Richer">
            <address>
              <email>openid@justin.richer.org</email>

              <uri>http://justin.richer.org/</uri>
            </address>
          </author>

          <date day="15" month="February" year="2016"/>
        </front>
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="HEART.OAuth2.FHIR"
                 target="http://openid.net/specs/openid-heart-oauth2-fhir.html">
        <front>
          <title>Health Relationship Trust Profile for OAuth 2.0</title>

          <author fullname="Justin Richer" initials="J." role="editor"
                  surname="Richer">
            <address>
              <email>openid@justin.richer.org</email>

              <uri>http://justin.richer.org/</uri>
            </address>
          </author>

          <date day="24" month="February" year="2017"/>
        </front>
      </reference>
    </references>

    <section anchor="Acknowledgements" title="Acknowledgements">
      <t>The OpenID Community would like to thank the following people for
      their contributions to this specification:</t>

      <t>Sarah Squire, Eve Maler, Luis Maas, Thomas Sullivan, Nancy Lush</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="Notices" title="Notices">
      <t>Copyright (c) 2017 The OpenID Foundation.</t>

      <t>The OpenID Foundation (OIDF) grants to any Contributor, developer,
      implementer, or other interested party a non-exclusive, royalty free,
      worldwide copyright license to reproduce, prepare derivative works from,
      distribute, perform and display, this Implementers Draft or Final
      Specification solely for the purposes of (i) developing specifications,
      and (ii) implementing Implementers Drafts and Final Specifications based
      on such documents, provided that attribution be made to the OIDF as the
      source of the material, but that such attribution does not indicate an
      endorsement by the OIDF.</t>

      <t>The technology described in this specification was made available
      from contributions from various sources, including members of the OpenID
      Foundation and others. Although the OpenID Foundation has taken steps to
      help ensure that the technology is available for distribution, it takes
      no position regarding the validity or scope of any intellectual property
      or other rights that might be claimed to pertain to the implementation
      or use of the technology described in this specification or the extent
      to which any license under such rights might or might not be available;
      neither does it represent that it has made any independent effort to
      identify any such rights. The OpenID Foundation and the contributors to
      this specification make no (and hereby expressly disclaim any)
      warranties (express, implied, or otherwise), including implied
      warranties of merchantability, non-infringement, fitness for a
      particular purpose, or title, related to this specification, and the
      entire risk as to implementing this specification is assumed by the
      implementer. The OpenID Intellectual Property Rights policy requires
      contributors to offer a patent promise not to assert certain patent
      claims against other contributors and against implementers. The OpenID
      Foundation invites any interested party to bring to its attention any
      copyrights, patents, patent applications, or other proprietary rights
      that may cover technology that may be required to practice this
      specification.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Purpose of Use">
      <t>The ability to specify information be made available for a specific
      purpose of use is key to many different medical information use cases.
      For example, a patient might determine that some things are available
      for research, while others are only available for treatment. At this
      time, these specifications do not define methods for indicating purpose
      of use beyond the "emergency access" claim defined in <xref
      target="emergency-access"/> and the "break the glass" mechanism defined
      in <xref target="break-the-glass"/>. The working group anticipates that
      expansion of this mechanism in implementations, which could lead to
      expansions of this protocol going forward.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Document History">
      <t>-2017-05-25</t>

      <t><list style="symbols">
          <t>Changed purpose of use examples from roles to actions</t>
        </list></t>

      <t>-2017-05-15</t>

      <t><list style="symbols">
          <t>Added note on purpose of use</t>
        </list></t>

      <t>-2017-04-29</t>

      <t><list style="symbols">
          <t>Minor wording tweak.</t>
        </list></t>

      <t>-2017-04-18</t>

      <t><list style="symbols">
          <t>Changed resource types to point to compartments instead of
          individual resource types</t>

          <t>Changed scopes to point to HEART OAuth FHIR scopes in entirety
          instead of being broken out</t>

          <t>Removed purpose of use claim (pou)</t>

          <t>Added a link to an example set of professional credential
          claims</t>

          <t>Added security considerations for claim provenance</t>
        </list></t>

      <t>-2017-03-20</t>

      <t><list style="symbols">
          <t>Clarified "er" scope</t>

          <t>Added reference to confidentiality and sensitivity scopes in
          HEART.OAuth.FHIR</t>

          <t>Changed "licenses" to "professional credentials"</t>
        </list></t>

      <t>-2017-02-24</t>

      <t><list style="symbols">
          <t>Added section on claims</t>

          <t>Added section on policy development</t>
        </list></t>

      <t>-2017-02-10</t>

      <t><list style="symbols">
          <t>Added scope and resource type requirements</t>

          <t>Created first semantic UMA profile</t>
        </list></t>
    </section>
  </back>
</rfc>
